Okay g RM G RM okay uh last
part is uh what is
it the conditions for theana okay ready
here we
go uh this is from the second G
room
uh if you ask a question what is the
group of conditions we need for vipasana
so generally shamata is a state of
concentration and vipasana is a insight
into how things work and ideally they
are married together
okay
right he gives
three three conditions that are helpful
for for
developing number one oh before you get
to hear
this is going to fit
17,500 I already put 2,000 in so I'm
going to start it over here and by the
time it reaches tahia it will have 17
and a half
maybe okay did you put mine in
there yeah let's do
it I'll give 2,000 don't be if you have
a credit card talk to jig May write a
piece of paper that says I give 16,000
and just put it in the in there and then
talk to her
afterwards no that's the difference
Jiggy Jiggy jig me write a check I need
that for something else that's for
something
else
just give her a check we can cancel it
before we
get okay here we go uh the first one
k uh find a good teacher find a good
teacher
about uh number two
mwa uh try to get lots of teachings on
emptiness try to get lots of teachings
on
emptiness in tibetan it's called M Thea
right many hearings of emptiness like
the pen 3,000 times I asked my teacher
how many times I have to listen to the
pen he said
3,000 so you have 2,900
left number
three syo uh think about those teachings
in the correct way think about the
teaching in the correct way so three
things you
need to understand emptiness
number one uh find someone who can teach
it uh number
two uh Seek many teachings on
it and then thirdly uh contemplate those
teachings in a good way okay okay here
we go he's going to explain each one in
more detail number
one
so he basically gives four qualities of
a good emptiness teacher
okay uh number one that teacher
themselves is M Thea they they have
learned many presentations on emptiness
so they can give it to you in many
different
ways the scriptures say that bodh saas
like to have a lot of detail on
emptiness and then people who are not
budhy saas they don't want much detail
okay
so if you want to be a buhis SAA you
have to learn a 100 ways to explain
emptiness okay that's what the
kamalashila meditations are they're just
aund ways to understand the same thing
okay number one
M what's
that clearly explain yeah I mean
sometimes like you want to learn piano
and the person's a really good piano
teacher but they're I'm sorry they're a
really good piano player but they're a
lousy
teacher and you find that sometimes you
know like the person's like a genius I
had that at Princeton all the teachers
my teachers in high school were better
than at Princeton the high school
teachers were good teachers at Princeton
they're all Geniuses and they don't like
to teach you know and it was it was
unpleasant uh
so that person should enjoy teaching
teaching and they should be a good
teacher they can explain it to you
easily okay in a clear
way number three NJ
danda uh they should do it out of love
they should teach out of love not for
money not to get
famous but they should teach because
they they love people and they want to
help them okay they want to help people
okay that's a third thing fourth thing
is
k k means
SK yo it means to get fed up with the
student uh and sua means you don't you
don't like you teach teach teach teach
they don't learn anything you repeat
repeat repeat repeat they complain
you're always
repeating then uh then they say bad
things about you for a couple years and
then you know then they come back and
they're ready to learn and you know you
have to K means that the teacher should
never get
discouraged or uh tired of of teaching
they should be like infinitely patient
and teachers can get all kinds of abuse
from students students can get abused by
teachers but but teachers can get abused
too and and you have to be patient you
know you just have to put up with it
okay if you have enough need
love then you put up with it okay and uh
it makes you a better teacher you know
you just learn to be patient with people
people won't people are like children
your children never thank you until
they're about 40 years
old okay it takes don't expect like
mothers don't take their children and
drop them off at a street corner and say
you're so ungrateful I'm tired tired of
you you know you know I actually I heard
about one person who did that and the
police God them anyway
uh but mothers generally don't drop
their kids off at a street corner and
say I'm so tired of you just go away you
know and and Buddhist teachers are the
same okay they treat their students like
their children and they no mother would
ever just dump their children somewhere
normally and uh even though those kids
are not going to be grateful or
acknowledge what you've done for maybe
40 years okay you just have to expect
that and for a mother it doesn't
matter traditionally there's one more
thing which is that if possible the
teacher has seen emptiness directly okay
if
possible the teacher has seen emptiness
directly uh
no matter how much the person has
studied and debated and spent time
learning uh if they haven't seen it
directly uh the the explanation will
always be a little bit wrong okay always
okay and there are very few people have
seen it directly okay so everybody else
is explaining what they heard an apple
taste
like and the person who's seen it
directly has has tasted the Apple so
they can give a better explanation and
the other explanations even if the
person is very careful to just repeat
what the lineage says it will never be
precise it will never be exactly correct
okay can't it cannot be okay and you can
smell the real Aras of History n Jona s
you can smell from their teachings that
they knew they they saw something and
they're describing it firsthand directly
okay so if you can try to find somebody
like
that okay
uh second one you know you should seek a
lot of teachings on
emptiness what does it mean to seek a
emptiness so traditionally all the
teachings of Lord are divided into 12
groups that's different from the Tria
the three
baskets or it's different from the
division of coner and tangar ands
boom and I don't have time today to give
you
a a a teaching on the 12 okay it's
complicated it's very complicated I'll
recite them for
you okay do means the
sutus means uh sort of like poetical
teachings l means
prophecies uh six means uh po
poetry okay the other one was more like
songs
gas means teachings that were delivered
to a specific group of students and they
were what do you call
it they were Twisted that way how do you
call it not Twisted
but they were geared for a special group
okay so they're a little bit
specialized then uh langi langi means uh
stories of incidents that happen and
triggered teachings okay uh to means uh
these are life stories of saints who are
not Buddhists okay
aanas like the teaching of the The Wheel
of Life comes from the udana aana
sometimes called the rudana aana it's
the story of King udana so this the
teaching on the Wheel of Life actually
comes through the story of the history
of King udana
okay
uh day the teachings on on what happened
I have no idea what that is I have to
look it
up means J Tales those are stories of
the Buddhist past lives okay that was
nine 10 is a shind day the extensive
teachings 11 is the med day which means
the amazing
teachings and 12 means the 10 La Day
means the the teachings that establish
things what does mean this a long story
okay the day I showed up at Sarah the
day I became am I had already studied
for eight years in with
r
and uh when I got there they said uh how
many years have you been when I became a
monk then they said how many years you
been staying I said eight years they
said okay we'll put you in Mika
class you know they put me in the eighth
year
class and my opponent is current my
opponent was the became the Abbot of G
tantu college so my opponent was the
Abbot of K T which means the next person
to hold the Throne of tonapa you know
and I did my first
debate and he's like okay give me the 12
divisions of the Buddhist teaching I'm
like
oh then afterwards I went to the
mother's store I said could I go back to
first grade could I just start with the
15-year-old kids and I started over I I
canell the eight years I started over I
started back at the beginning uh
debating and it was it was a good it
took a lot of courage to do it but it
was the best thing I ever did okay Papa
so learn all
the teachings of the Buddha how he
teaches emptiness in 12 different parts
of his teachings okay for example in The
Wheel of Life teaching which is actually
part of the Buddhist history
books there's a famous Sutra called what
I really meant who wrote
it yeah the Buddha he wrote a book
called what I really
meant that was in the third the third
stage of his teachings in the in the
first stage of Lord Buddha teachings he
didn't teach much emptiness in the
second stage he only taught
emptiness and then everybody complained
everybody criticized him so in the third
stage of his teaching he taught M only
he went backwards he said oh I I didn't
mean everything's empty and he he he
compromised what he was saying and then
at the end of all three periods of his
life people said which one was the
truth and and he wrote a book called
which one was the
truth which one was the
truth the second okay not the second
turning of the wheel
okay know that book in which Lord Buddha
says what he was really thinking he says
if you don't want to reach lockdown
don't
study don't get more teachings on
emptiness if you if you don't want to
reach
vasana then don't go to many teachings
on emptiness okay just stay
home Okay g means that will block Viana
if you don't get many different
teachings on
emptiness
the same book
says uh if you want to get Viana you
have to go the through the traditional
three steps
of classroom
time contemplating at home and then
meditating on it at Diamond Mountain
okay okay you that's where it comes
from
uh so this is a a Sutra called the Sutra
of
narayana which is a common name in the
Hindu tradition right but uh in tibetan
it's seu which means the child who is
free of Desire is narayana is the
literal meaning of narayana okay and
there's a Sutra called the Sutra
requested by narana okay it's actually a
a jaw what's a
jaw it's a mantra it's a book about
mantras okay and I think it's missing
Jigme in the in the I think it's in the
d k so we might want to recover
it okay
uh only people who go to lots of
teachings will develop wisdom only
people who go to lots of teachings will
develop
wisdom
only those who have wisdom will be able
to put an end to their negative emotions
okay like the husband thing right you we
say there are conventional ways to keep
your patience you know count to
10 you know look at the
steing you know but we say ultimately
the only way to destroy patients
permanently is to understand then that
the person you're angry at is not
there because you can only be angry at a
person if you think they're not coming
from you okay so in in Buddhism that's
the only way only by understanding The
Emptiness of your husband can you be
patient with him it doesn't refer to his
stomach which is always empty I
know all men's stomach are empty they
are born with empty stomach they have to
eat all day
okay uh and don't forget uh the word for
shamata incorporates the word for sha to
put something to rest okay so it's a
pun uh okay third one what does it mean
to think correctly about those
teachings what does it mean to think
about the teachings
correctly you have to spend a lot of
time decide studying all the schools the
four Great schools of
Buddhism and understand why three and a
half of them are incorrect okay there
are four ancient schools of Buddhism in
India right the Abid Dharma
schools the logic schools uh the mind
only school and the two parts of the
middle way School the lower part of the
middle way School the M only School the
schools and the aid schools all have
mistakes they all have they all have
mistakes in them okay who who put the
mistakes in
them yeah Lord Buddha
why I don't know he was teaching
in Paris and he said you know your
husband's not really there and somebody
said I don't understand well you know
and he said well you know the husband
who's not your fault is not there and
they said no I still don't get it and
and then finally they said okay look
your husband is
there and it's his fault but just be
nice to him okay and because he was
trying to help the people who couldn't
get it okay then unfortunately they
wrote those teachings
down and those became the lower schools
okay
so the process of contemplating what you
learned about emptiness has to involve
learning to separate
what the Buddha really meant and what
the Buddha didn't really mean and the
line is always drawn by was he talking
about emptiness or not okay if he wasn't
talking about
emptiness he he didn't get to say what
he wanted to say there was some problem
you know like the auditorium had to
close or the speaker wasn't working
or okay when he has time and an audience
to say what he wants to say he always
adds emptiness okay all right uh so you
have to learn to divide the
teachings dup otherwise you will always
be in doubt you will always have doubts
you will always have hesitations I don't
quite understand what he's talking about
you know he taught mind only school and
then he taught
Middle Way school and they don't match
each other and I don't get it then
you'll always be having
doubt and it took me a long time to
figure out this word he says you'll be
like those you know those bamboo pole
and it has two things you're carrying
two
buckets he says you'll always be like
this person you know this was it my only
School correct or was the middleway
school career and you carry them both
around all the time like this and you'll
never be comfortable you'll always be
wondering which one is
correct
lakor chin you'll be like a person who
reached a what do they call that E
Cummings poem I reached
the there's a poem about reaching the
path less
taken Robert Frost
sorry yeah anyway he gets to a point
where there's two paths you know and he
doesn't know which one goes home or
which one he should take and in that
poem it's it's one of the most famous
pieces of American poetry American
Poetry is 1% as long as Chinese
poetry really so we have like this many
PS uh but that's one famous one I came
to the in the forest in the snow I came
to a split in the road and I'm trying to
decide which go which way to go and I
saw one is less less people went that
way so I decided to go that way okay so
it means uh if you don't learn all the
schools clearly then you'll always be
confused and and you'll be like the guy
trying to decide which way to go
okay you won't be able to decide which
school you agree with then he he's
finished with the causes for bana he's
finished but he throws in something else
which andriana's really gonna
like
okay he says by the
way
uh yogis should eat
properly okay if you're gonna try to
develop an understanding of emptiness
you have to be careful what you eat
and that's so strange for a great
philosopher you know 1,300 years ago
pauses and says don't eat junk
food and he puts it right there in the
middle of emptiness teaching you know he
says don't eat junk food okay he says
don't eat kand don't eat McDonald's kick
them out of China kick them out of China
kick them out of
China
tell the Americans to bring something
useful okay
like Kung
F that's a good
one aoga a yogi should never eat NY or
sha fish meat or any other kind of meat
okay A a meditator who wants to develop
shamat and Viana should not eat meat
okay he said it I didn't say it
okay give it
up don't eat things that don't go well
like eat watermelon in the
winter with
noodles okay it will cause a revolution
in your stomach
okay uh and don't eat things that that
make you sleep
and you can't meditate well
okay then the big thing for us
boys say to simber sour say say
say
s say
sin not bad
uh judge the quantity of what you eat
with extreme care you know eat bite by
bite bite eat a bite then see how it
feels you know do you still feel light
do you still feel bright then if you do
you can take another bite and and as
soon as you start to feel a little heavy
stop and it doesn't matter that the
restaurant gave you a big
plate okay learn to ignore the size of
an American Plate okay you know when I
got out threee Retreat uh somebody took
me to like Disneyland
it was very
cruel and uh they gave me French fries
this many this much French fries on a
plate and there was loud music playing
and there was a mechanical bowl with a
person on
it and I was I was like this you know
and I was like how many people are
supposed to eat these french fries they
said that's for you and I'm like I don't
believe it you know so eat by bite by
bite you know take a bite and then see
how's my stomach your stomach should be
a little bit
empty still they say one quarter empty
and then and then stop fill your stomach
three
quarters and then stop when you still
feel a little bit light okay and and
that can only be judged bite by bite you
you cannot put a bunch of food on a
plate and say I'm going to finish all
that you have to see how you feel okay
and it took me 50 years it took me 60
years you know I'm trying to save you
some
time you know and uh don't eat
everything people give you your friends
give you
cookies just say thank you very much if
you're at the
airport and people give you a bag of
chocolates then say thank you so much
you know and go through their customs
and throw them out don't even give them
to anybody cuz that they'll make
somebody else sick you see what I mean
so so you know don't eat what people
give you okay if it's not healthy donate
it
okay I'm really happy about the juices
here I'm really happy I think they
helped a lot uh the classes people were
very bright during the classes and
people were sitting there for over 3
hours did you notice you didn't even
notice cuz your stomachs were empty and
uh you were having green drinks and
stuff so uh it's perfect for meditation
and when you see Michel
and tahia and
kunga and
G uh these people got up at
4:00 to make you your juices okay your
green juices and your orange juices
yeah
and before the retreat they were working
like insane like two three months four
months before they were working all day
very hard like carrying beds and you
know heavy things not like our work you
know here like somebody says I want an
extra bed in Earl's cabin you know then
that's a 4-Hour thing you know and you
it's heavy and just to get there is
dangerous on the road and they do it all
day every day thank you thank you for
that yeah all the bedding she bought all
new blankets all new sheets all new
mattresses uh she bought the whole thing
so I'd like to thank
her
and the lady who keeps the water going
and the solar going retired Nicole Davis
the one who built the student center and
she retired after that cuz her husband
lost his jobs they had to
move so gal's been running around fixing
all the solar and all the water and I'd
like to thank her for
that so
yeah and Joe Joe's been helping Joe
helps a lot water but it's very
difficult the the whole water it's our
own water system it's a it's very
complicated it's five miles of pipes
there are five miles of pipes and and
it's very difficult the whole thing is
crazy and she takes care of
it okay last thing he says Chu
first get those conditions together then
go into meditation okay first get those
conditions together and then go into
meditation
okay the conditions for shamata and the
conditions
for for
meana okay we're going to do okay I'm
going to skip the meditation let's do it
tomorrow
all right all
right let's do it
now do now you busting
me let's do something
today I mean Mondays are really good day
to start
stuff
I tried James I
tried I was just seeing if it would if
you would notice or
not okay so don't forget for the next
two months or
so uh when you have time if you get up
early enough
then do the whole thing you know do the
preparations bring your llama there then
watch your body is it still then watch
your
breath and then watch what Buddha future
Buddha okay and if you have a lot of
time interrupt your future Buddha
meditation to see if you
are still on the object and then to see
how's the quality of your attention okay
are you tired or are you distracted
basically okay here we
go blow your
nose turn off your cell phone
Unfortunately they work down
here you can still record if you
want
but if it goes
off it's
$50
yeah we did that in Mexico it's it's
amazing how fast people learn to turn
off their
phone I'm going to do alandro system he
gets
$49 and the the center gets a dollar
also
okay you
ready okay
relax relax your
forehead relax your
hands relax your shoulders bring your
shoulder blades
together pull in your lower abdomen just
a little
bit
and then come to your
breath
lightly
then focus on your body I'm sorry let's
do the
preliminar bring your
llama ask them to
come
for
make them an
offering sorry let's do something else
first think of something beautiful about
them that you really
admire
for
then make them an offering something
nice you
did in the last few days I
think you you could offer all the hard
work you did and Retreat some most
people here did two
Retreats it wasn't
easy
for
then admit to your teacher something you
didn't do so well
yesterday maybe a negative thought about
somebody
then again something nice you
did this week or you saw somebody
do something
like the amazing work that people do to
keep dond Mountain
going
for
then ask your teacher to teach
you keep
teaching
and then ask your teacher to stay your
life
now bring your mind to your
body focus on your
body and we'll sit completely still for
minutes we won't move for 5
minutes try not to move your
fingers or your
eyes or your forehead or your mouth for
five
minutes the object of meditation is your
body
for
okay
now come to your
breath check your
forehead
search
for the sweet spot where your focus
increases
and start to see the breath coming
out of that spot in your
forehead
now see the lower
belly pushing in slightly to make the
breath come out of the
forehead very slightly but keep up the
muscular tension there don't let it go
but don't
string
now bring the inhale in through the top
of your
shoulders it
Narrows down to the lower
back focus on long exhales let the
inhales take care of
themselves but do feel that
motion of Prana down your
back starting wider like your shoulders
and narrowing at the
bottom
long exhales natural
inhales
now we'll come to the main object of the
meditation you are above the sky you're
on the edge of that black outer
space you are
watching across the top of the
sky and you can see
yourself as a Buddha you will
be
sorry the next time the Bell
Rings see if your
focus is still on the
Buddha gazing
down on a world of people they are
taking care
of
for
what's your mind on the Buddha future
Buddha
we try one more
time
for
stay in
meditation now we'll check the quality
of the
meditation so when the bell rings a
second
time in my am I
wandering or am I
sleepy or am I enjoying being a Buddha
and it's so
enjoyable I didn't get sleepy and I
didn't think about lunch or
airports
for
e
okay one more
time when the bell goes
off is my
mind enjoying the
object or is it thinking about something
else or is it just dull
sleepy
for
okay come back to your
breath when you exhale imagine
you're giving away all the good
karma we did during this
meditation and a hard week of classes
hard week of
Meditation
Retreat
give it to your country give it to your
world then you can come out and
stretch
okay top
Q horse race horse
race that's what the Llama has to do
when there's not much time
left
T horse
race
we have three more
meditations in the original text and if
I have time I don't know I I'll try to
tell you where the original
text Cuts you know Cuts according to the
meditations
but the Buddha starts another part here
in the Sutra he
says
when a shares things with other people
they don't only don't stay in
things they don't stay in anything at
all okay he says nothing at all they
don't stay in nothing at
all
why the bodh SAA can
give can share things without staying in
anything at
all the good karma that they make is
like a
mountain say
somea it's difficult to measure
okay and then kamila says Master kamila
says H Jo we were just thanking you for
all the water but anyway you were in
here so
then then uh Master kamila makes two
points here first point
uh that bodh Safa when they share things
they don't even get caught in thinking
that emptiness comes from its own side
okay so when he
says they don't think of
anything uh they don't stay anywhere at
all he means they even understand that
Emptiness is coming from them okay then
when we were in Taiwan
freezing uh that was cold
um
that was a funny
story I told them if they were really
purifying their karma it would
snow and the next morning it
snowed first time in like a 100
years and it was funny it wasn't funny
uh
anyway this is a difficult point you
know so now he's come to the emptiness
of things that don't change he covered
the three kinds of things that do change
which is physical things knowing
things and and Concepts like John
okay or or a karmic seed which is a
potential it's not physical it's not
mental it stays in the mind but it's not
mental because it doesn't know
anything okay uh we covered all the
unchanging
we hey the the people who got up at 4:00
to make your juice every
morning
we also want to be at every class
yeah they also lost a lot of other sleep
not just a jeice
sleep what they do in Guang Joo is the
day after gishi Michael leaves they
sleep for two
weeks
okay uh
so we covered The Emptiness of changing
things all three kinds of changing
things uh people right the people who
reached nirvana for example we covered
The Emptiness of physical things like
elephants and we covered The Emptiness
of mental things
like uh the mind which holds an
aspect and the string of thoughts in the
mind we covered emptiness of all those
changting
things now we're going to one of the
only unchanging things which is
emptiness okay and it's a difficult
thing we talked about it in Taiwan
uh it's a natural question to ask Gesa
is emptiness also coming popping out of
my caric seeds because if it is it must
be changing because it has a cause you
know something produced it which is of
varying power it spts out the emptiness
and then it declines like a line wave
right so if if karmic seeds are spitting
out all things then emptiness also must
be coming out of karmic seeds and when
the Buddha in the diamond color Sutra
says that the bodh SATA doesn't even
think that emptiness comes from its own
side well the only other option from
coming from your own side is it's coming
from my karmic seeds so if it's coming
from my karmic seeds how can it be
unchanging okay
okay and here you have to understand
that unchanging means
uh never varying in its quality never
varying in its quality
okay and Emptiness is that emptiness
doesn't get more or less ever it's
always the
same quantity it's always the same
unvarying for
example if I ask you is there
a twoe
headed 30 m High elephant in this room
you can
say purple elephant okay you can say no
okay how much is it not
here 100% okay 100% does it does it ever
get 90% not here cuz then there'd be
just the foot of the elephant in the
door you see what I mean like you either
the elephant's in here or the elephant's
not in here now get this because a
purple elephant cannot exist it
especially couldn't be
here okay cuz they can't exist anyway
okay is there a purple elephant at the
front door no is there a purple elephant
halfway in no is there a purple elephant
all the way in no is there a husband who
yells at you because you didn't yell at
your kids no no no
okay that in the end that's what we're
talking about the purpose of emptiness
is to make you happy and successful you
got to tie it to your husband and your
income and your state of mind and your
world right it has to be relevant to
your life okay so we're not just talking
about purple elephants can a husband
irritating husband walk in the
door who's not your fault
how much can he not walk in the
door 100% okay
100% now his not walking in the door is
coming from
somewhere and it's coming from your
seeds okay so your seeds produce a thing
that isn't
there your your seeds produce the
absence of a husband who could never
exist you got to get used to that okay
you're seeds are
producing the absence of a husband who
is not coming from
you got
it it's coming out of your seats and
it's constant it never changes but it's
coming out of your seats okay it's not
that tomorrow he can be 90% not coming
from you or something like that he's
constant okay I gave the example I like
to give the example of a fountain so if
you ever want what's that fountain in
Rome Trey
Trevy yeah they throw money in there
they encourage the tourists to throw
money in there I went there late at
night and the city workers were taking
all the money
out and uh the fountain has a shape if
the water pressure is constant the
fountain has a shape so the shape is
being supplied by a constant changing
flow of water water seeds are opening
but the shape is constant the shape is
unchanging you see the flow is is new
water every second but the general shape
of the Veni
venen try
whatever that's constant if the water
pipe doesn't change if the water
pressure doesn't change you know it's
going to always look the same in the
outline but it's it's new SE is
constantly pushing it out okay
the the fact that the husband who's not
your fault cannot be in the room never
changes okay but it's still flowing out
of your
seats two questions at H is
first what it make it constant I in
order to say it's
not it's changing but it's constant also
I didn't say it was changing no the
seeds are changing but the shape is not
changing what the mean of constant yeah
constant means if it doesn't vary it
doesn't it's not like he's
1% my fault and sorry he's 1% his fault
tomorrow then the next day he's 5% his
fault he's never ever any% his fault
it's always 100% your fault he's the
husband who is not your fault is always
100% not
here and it can't be more or less and
Emptiness is like that but what actually
make that se constant what I like once
in Taiwan you talk about when you ask R
yeah why there were six kind of beans
and that's also empty why there are not
like many others like like looks like
the end something is as you say constant
and it has to be constant but it's
dangerous the line between constant and
self-existent yeah yeah yeah very good
thing where how something that is not
self-existent is coming from my always
be constant like almost like a rule like
like yeah always come out the same
way uh it's called patterns it
means of all all possibilities in the
world of all the ways that things can
happen in 165th of a second all the ways
they can
interact countless things can interact
in 165th of a second it it it's only so
many
possibilities only 65 seats yeah yeah
it's
only yeah that also comes you can change
that can change I mean that can change
when you're in the dentist chair and
time slows down you know you asked the
dentist how long how long were you
drilling on my teeth he says 10 minutes
he said no no it must have been an
hour okay like that you're with your
girlfriend you're kissing her in the
movie
theater 3 hours goes by in about five
minutes okay so
anyway you someone asked my I'm I I hate
to say it with my AR enemy art but uh he
asked a question to my llama he
said are all unchanging things
absences and my llama said
yes and maybe that will help you maybe
there's some help there all unchanging
things are something
missing yeah so
then in the absence is something that's
produced or the lab
the labels produced you can say that the
is no oh
well yeah I know what you
mean it's a pattern that comes from
seeds opening yes but it's not a result
of seeds opening you can't say it's a
result the itself yeah you can't say
that otherwise it would it would be
changing because a seed spurts and and
and degrades it it always goes like that
maybe it's that the next seed is always
there on time to keep it
constant like the flow of water in a in
a
fountain so so this is the thing that
doesn't come from the
absence uh the absence of the husband
who comes he the absence
itself well the perception the absence
has to come from seeds because all
things have to come from seeds all
perceptions yeah does the absence itself
come from seeds maybe you can say no I
think you have to say
no oh so it's
there the perception of the absence
comes from
SS is always there quality and comp is
constant yeah and can we see is have
self-existence
no that's what he just asked that's what
he just
asked uh maybe things can come in a
pattern the same pattern all the time
but not from their own
side there maybe there's something
constant about you which makes the same
pattern all the time but it doesn't mean
it self-existent can that pattern change
huh can that change
no but it's not self-existent
that means some changing made this
unchanging changing the SE cause the
perception of it
yeah does that mean when the SE is open
uh you can see the s from your SE that's
physical SC or whatever with it absence
yeah EMP together yeah that's okay yeah
so the
all things have their own emptiness yeah
all things are like your husband so the
in of The Emptiness is also from our
seat what's that emptiness yeah we make
the things and they have emptiness so
you can
see come two
results yeah there's always four results
from a comic scene no
problem
okay let's get going or or we cannot
finish okay
so Master kashila says why did the
Buddha start talking again about how
bodh safas don't stay in things when
they give he repeats himself first he
said they don't stay in those six
objects of your census but then he
repeat them he repeats and he says they
don't stay in
anything and by that he means they don't
even stay in the
emptiness that they understand when
they're giving now sexy sexy
sexy we have a strange idea of sexy
right uh then he says
well why why don't they stand anything
well their their generosity has massive
results what
this is the conversation do they stay in
emptiness
no why they're their generosity has
massive
results which is to say if you if you
share things with an understanding that
I put the person here who's getting the
thing I created the gift that I'm giving
them and I created me to give the gift
cuz it's only with that awareness that
you will want to keep giving because you
understand that's what gave you the
stuff to give in the first place the
minute you get some money the best you
can do is recycle
it okay so that's an understanding of
The Emptiness of money okay if you
understand the emptiness of money you
can't hold it for too long
okay then then he says and that bua
generosity has massive results and then
Kamala Sheila says he's answering the
aspirin
question Buddha is addressing the
aspirin question
uh if an aspirin is empty does it still
work
normally no it's a more
complicated okay here yeah it has to be
loaded like a stapler okay will does a
stapler
work sometimes if it has staples it
works if it's out of Staples it doesn't
work okay aspirin is the same you take a
something for a headache sometimes it
works sometimes it doesn't work that's
because it's either loaded or it's not
loaded how do you load medicine
you help other people with headaches
okay and then that loads the medicine
then when you take the medicine a week
after helping somebody at work with a
heada it will work for you and if you
don't it won't the same medicine and
that's why every year they come out with
a new medicine and say this
one really works really works this one
really works okay there will never be a
medicine that really works except
helping other people with
headaches but then the question comes
okay but then the question comes do you
still have to take an
aspir sometimes
okay like if the Aspen is empty can it
do
anything and then I taught you that in
DCI give me the Wimpy answer and then
give me the strong
answer okay if the Aspen is empty does
it
work it works even though it's empty
okay that's the Wimpy answer that's the
that's that's the stupid that's like low
low intelligent
answer does the Aspen work even though
it's
empty and then and then yeah and then a
lower understanding will say even though
it's empty it
works and then a higher understanding
says look if it wasn't empty there'd be
no place for my seats to operate and it
couldn't work it's only because it empty
that it works okay all right if the if
the aspir wasn't empty it couldn't work
okay and that's really hard that's
really hard I had a guy I'll never
forget he was a very famous journalist
in Ireland and he came to a tiny little
class in gway maybe Michael was there I
don't know we were in gway it was tiny
little
class and he got angry when I got to
this point he got very angry he had just
skipped out to uh
interview
Bono and he was you know he said I have
to leave the class I said come on why he
says there's a bar across the street I'm
interviewing Bono from you two I said
all right
and and then he came back in and he he
said I gave the aspirin talk and then he
said listen are you
suggesting that a automobile could get
from gallway to what's the other city in
Ireland
Dublin the whole population of Ireland
is one tenth of gong Jong
anyway he he said are you suggesting
that I could get to Dublin in a car with
no gas if I've been giving a lot of
people
rhides and I said yes and he said that's
and then he uh
like two weeks later he
died he he walked through a glass door
and he died it was really bizarre it was
really strange you know and
uh anyway
uh yeah it's possible like somebody will
invent
a a solar car that's okay that's where
solar cars come from okay like you have
to understand that okay
so the Buddha says sorry kamalashila
says the reason why the Buddha mentioned
that the giving the sharing has a big
result was that he wanted to say that
even though the sharing is empty it
still does something or on a deeper
level that's why it can do anything okay
got it and to measure the results of
that kind of generosity is May it's not
easy to measure
okay got
it uh does an aspen work or
not yes sometimes uh then we say things
that work sometimes don't work you don't
get on an airplane if the startist says
sometimes they fall down sometimes they
they work if you ask the startist you
know do do these ples always reach the
other city and she says sometimes then
you go to another airline you see you
won't get on an airplane if she says
sometimes they fall down sometimes they
fly you see
you something works if it works all the
time right will you buy a car if it only
works three days a week you know you
won't buy it you say give me a car that
works seven days a week right
so aspirin only works sometimes because
sometimes you have karma in your mind
from from taking care of other people
with a headache if you have that karma
in your mind the aspirin will work for
you if you didn't take care of other
people the aspirin won't work for you
the same aspirin so the power in the
aspirin is not in the
chemicals it's in the karma okay of the
person who who eats it if they have good
karma the aspirin will work if they
don't it it won't work that's the
emptiness of
aspirin that's the emptiness of aspirin
but in order to make sure that work we
have to always do their Cofe meditation
right yeah sure you have to share
uh my experience in can we use a
microphone be
helpful yeah so it's from my experience
I think um I help people a lot but
somehow I couldn't get their good comma
back yeah so I think my seat like
couldn't open it's like stuck right yeah
it's because yeah you didn't
enjoy uh it enough you didn't have
enough fun later you didn't say oh that
was really cool that I gave some people
aspirin at work but somehow you know I
feel happy whenever I do the things that
um uh some people they say if we just
keep thinking about it like we uh we we
selfish or we um don't give or the
generosity to others yeah is so how like
um the copy meditation has to combine
with their planting seeds it puts water
on the scene yeah it puts water on the
seat by the way the best question I ever
had about this conversation came in U I
think it was gong Jong do you remember
the
question do you guys
remember some young man asked a very
good question about
this he said wait just stop you know
stop this whole conversation I said why
he said it doesn't make sense and I said
why and he
says so if I want my Aspen to work for
me the next time I get a headache then I
have to give aspirin to everybody at
work who gets a headache I cannot ignore
another person that I hear has a
headache I said that's right he says but
come on the aspin you're giving to them
doesn't
work it was such a good question you
know he says come on you're going to
give them Aspen but maybe it won't work
so what kind of karma you going to get
you know how can your asand work if
you're handing out asand that don't work
you know what's the
answer it's intention how much love do
you have how much love do you have when
you hand out aspirin that might not
work okay whose fault is it that the
aspirin doesn't work yeah it's their
fault okay but you have to keep giving
you have to try you have to try oh boy
too many
questions okay we're going to go over a
little bit that's okay
yeah all right but my breakfast still
okay J mic so the only way to get rid of
your headache is to teach someone else
about
emptiness yeah ultimately in the end
yeah
y you you sorry you might get a body
that's made of light or something that
never gets
headaches okay holy llama I I wonder if
you might comment also on the deeper
aspect of the teaching in this Diamond
Cutter Sutra there is a clear contrast
between people that are covering planets
with jewels people that are giving and
then giving without
staying the giving without staying by
staying in
emptiness that is immeasurable these
other things are appearances so I wonder
if you can can uh comment on that he's
going to he's going to that's the line
that comes next that's the next
meditation it's coming we're going to we
have to get to
that another
question
yeah when you
describe that if you have the seed by
taking the aspirin the aspirin will work
that implies that taking the aspirin
will make that seed
ripen that does not sound precise uh
if the karmic seed ripens yeah if the
aspirin will work yeah if
the seed is planted with all four stamps
so if it's a Karma Mara and not just a
Karma uh then it then it will ripen on
time yeah so when you take the aspirin
you think of your karma Marga uh is that
loading it that's not get it to work no
like for a few nights after you help
people at work you have to enjoy and
think about how smart you are cuz you're
loading your
aspirins yeah and then and then take the
aspirin and it will work yeah because
the being happy about offering other
people aspirin Waters the seed and
technically Prana is being carried to
the seed
because
because Prana and thought always follow
each other when you focus on
a good seed you planted mentally Prana
always carries to the same area and
heats the seed Pally and it has to open
well then why take the aspirin at all
yeah that's a good I knew you're going
to ask me
that uh if the seed is strong enough you
don't have to take an aspin it's true uh
potato chips sometimes
works I found chocolate chip cookies
uh and I asked the doctor I said how
come when I eat like six chocolate chip
cookies my hyd goes away and he's like
it expands the blood vessels or I don't
know uh but yeah it's true that if your
karma was intense enough uh you wouldn't
have to take an aspirin you could take a
glass of water or something like
that and then you get into what we call
Miracles you know like the seeds are so
powerful that
that Stones can sing or you can walk on
water and things like that yeah you you
pass from
normal possibilities into Miracles yeah
do you want to take let's do it's up to
you yeah let's take one more and two
more thank you thank you L um I guess
I'm still a little confused about what
it means to not be staying in emptiness
because if you're staying in emptiness
then you're understanding The Emptiness
of everything therefore the bodh wait we
have to say something else okay the
instructions from Buddha here was don't
stay right don't stay in things don't it
means don't keep thinking it's your
husband's
fault I thought I had heard and possibly
I heard it but you didn't say it they
were not they're also not staying in
emptiness so that's where my confusion
is not staying in an emptiness which is
not coming from from you in an in an
emptiness which is not coming from you
and because that emptiness doesn't exist
it's just like the husband who doesn't
come from you okay so does the body s
stay in
emptiness yes yes does he stay in an
emptiness which is not coming from him
no no okay got it there's two husbands
in the room and there's two emptinesses
in the
room and one of them doesn't exist
because that's the emptiness
of that is not coming from the bodh SAA
okay and that's the last
misunderstanding you'll ever have is
about emptiness itself you know you will
think somehow emptiness comes from its
own
side R thank you Lama so if giving money
uh the result of that is having money I
can quit my job
tomorrow well that's a thing that's
Susan's question it's the same
question uh if the karma is powerful
enough you can quit your job and checks
will be sent to you and I always give
the example of uh someone handed me
$100,000 check in a diamond Mentor
class uh after I quit my job I didn't
have a job and someone had that's how we
built a five miles of water system it
came from that $100,000 someone handed
me a check I never met them before and
um
yeah if the karma is extremely powerful
it doesn't need a
postman but that's that's pretty
far okay yeah other
question
uh once I heard from you saying that uh
if you have really good seats when you
are having headache you can just drink a
glass of uh chocolate and it will help
then you said then you should try you
said then later you said um if you have
really good seeds you won't even have
headaches so can you explain more yeah
what you said is really nice uh if you
help people at work who have headaches
with a lot of skill and with a lot of
compassion and with a lot of
understanding
emptiness uh that headache that you were
supposed to have becomes
a a future event that doesn't
happen a future event that never happens
it's a it's a special word in Buddhism
so you were supposed to have a headache
next week but you did so much coffee
meditation on giving other people
medicine at work headache medicine at
work that it just doesn't happen it just
never happens okay yeah that's true so
the 24th meditation
here if help the sick makes medicine
work for me do I still have to take the
medicine what's the
answer normally you do you know at our
level you do you still have to take an
aspirin but at a higher level you won't
have to take an aspirin
okay and then at a higher level as
Jasmine said you'll just never get
headaches anymore anyway okay it the
karma will stop them before they
come yes m'am oh yeah
jenjen
Stanley okay go ahead Stanley he's got
the
microphone uh gisha I just want to U
confirm with you about the emptiness
coming from SE thing so one time Earl
ask you a question and you say you can
plant things out of a ground but the
ground is not the cause of the plant but
the C is so compared to this metaphor
you say The Emptiness is coming from SE
not as a pattern not as
a result because result always changes
yeah you can't call a result of a cost
yeah uh like when my seat for a pen
ripens another picture of my mic come
out at the same time as you said before
the emptiness will show come into
existence as the object exists that's
okay
at that moment what
happened uh between the ripening of the
seed and the emptiness of the pen yeah
you have to think like this
okay and this is something you have to
meditate on okay there's two kinds of
impermanence there's two kinds of
changing one is called subtle one is
called
gross and it's a big subject of
meditation we talked about it in level
seven
DCI and you just have to think about it
tell you but you have to think about it
uh does this glass have
emptiness yeah all glasses have
emptiness what's the emptiness of this
glass is the fact that it's not not
coming from
me to not okay is it coming from you yes
is it not coming from you no is it not
not coming from you yes okay the fact
that it's not coming from
you sorry the fact that it's not not
coming from you is its emptiness okay
now the glass is impermanent meaning
changing it was produced in a factory it
started out as you know liquid glass and
then it they shaped it and then it
became a glass and then it will break
someday it will break
um can if it changing thing has
emptiness and it breaks does the
changing
thing change sorry does the emptiness
change no we say it goes out of
existence but we don't say it changes
it's not like when the glass starts to
break I drop the glass it touches the
floor the first crack starts does the
emptiness get 90% empty you see what I
mean it cannot
it either it's either it's not not
coming from me or it is there's no
choice there's no choice it's only one
or the other okay so the did the
glass break yes was the glass destroyed
yes was The Emptiness was The Emptiness
destroyed we say no did it go out of
existence we say yes it doesn't go like
this it's more more more more ESS and
then it gets old and it's less less less
less emptiness it's not like the glass
the glass looks like
this people look like this countries
look like
this right but Emptiness is
just and it's gone okay because it
depends on the
glass okay it's very difficult but if
you understand that you will answer your
question your question will be answered
okay emptiness comes into existence when
the glass is produced at the last minute
that the glass is formed in the factory
its emptiness comes into existence but
it doesn't
startop and the day you break the glass
it's its emptiness goes out of existence
but it doesn't end okay it doesn't go
like this because if it ended it would
Peter out it would get less less less
less less and then there'd be more and
more purple elephant in the
room get it okay it's a difficult idea
that's subtle in permanence and it's Mis
explained in many books in many
scriptures
okay all right Jen Jen and her friend
had a
question uh gisha so you were teaching
about three Spears right like uh uh the
object me and the thing that I'm giving
they're both empty uh so if I'm using it
in my real life uh because for example
if I offer something to you you and you
are empty so I can say that you are a
Buddha and if I am empty then I can say
that I am a Buddha and then the thing
that I'm offering you because it's empty
that I can say that this is a Seas for
me to get enlightened uh how should I
think it in a correct way should I think
that you are a Buddha or you can be a
Buddha which means like potentially that
you can be a Buddha or should I say that
I can be a Buddha or I am a Buddha like
what is the correct way
of thinking when you're doing offerings
with the understanding of three Spears
in the in the open teachings you
think
okay
in
Tantra
uh you believe all three Spirits are
already Divine already inl I'm I'm
already
Buddha I'm giving this flower to a
Buddha and the flower itself came from a
Buddha Paradise okay in in Tantra it's
called result vehicle right you you IM
you pretend that you're already at the
goal because it helps you get there
faster okay so that's a short answer but
it's a beautiful answer okay it never
hurts we don't know that the person
we're giving the flower to is a Buddha
or not so you might as well pretend
they're Buddha then the flower becomes
very powerful okay
Shing uh just now about the meditation
24 you mentioned that if we reach some
level then we don't need the uh as
springs for example but my question is
that about which level for can can you
tell which level for example like first
body s second body sver or one who has
reached uh who has the emptiness the r
sea or he need to be a Buddha thank you
I would say there's a big thing
happening uh at the seventh bodh sta
level okay uh generally the seventh body
s level is very important it's called
ring Thea going
far and uh it was the subject of my GUI
debate so I I remember
it and uh generally at the seventh body
s level some amazing things are
happening between 7th and 8th
okay so I I off hand I'd say that okay
generally I'd say
that okay come
on let's leave it so I have to see you
again in
guara okay last meditation
okay here's the
text what do you
think can you measure this the edge of
the Sky by walking to the
east can you walk to the east for three
miles and then look up and say that's
where the sky
ends it's like trying to find the rain
the pot of gold at the bottom of the
rainbow you keep walking towards the
rainbow and it keeps moving
okay so Bud respectfully replied Buddha
it's not then the Buddha said uh is it
true also of the South and the west and
then the North and up and down which are
the and the eight ordinal
directions uh you know is it easy to
measure and and he uses the word for sky
but it also means outer space I mean
space in the sense of place can you
reach the end of the universe right by
walking
East then the and
then uh the Buddha says
sorry so buddy says yeah it's not
can't you can't measure it you can't
measure how far the space goes how far
the Universe goes then the Buddha says
uh that's how much Good Karma the body
sappa makes by thinking about emptiness
when they share things with other people
okay that's how much Good Karma they
make when they share things with other
people and think about emptiness
okay then
kamila he says Uh there's
three three kinds of big going on here
okay number
one Buddha is comparing that good karma
to the sky because the sky touches all
things okay the sky touches the trees
the sky touches the mountains the sky
touches the Lakes the sky touches all
the
people The Good Karma that that body St
is doing affects all people in the
universe okay it ripples out to all
people in the
universe number
two uh it extends
infinitely okay it affects people even
on other planets
okay and then thirdly it's inexhaustible
it never ends okay it won't end why if
if I uh give some
money on understanding The Emptiness of
that money which is that it wasn't
printed by the US
government it was created by my past
generosity okay the money wasn't printed
by the US government it was created
because because I was generous in the
past then the minute that money touches
my hands if I have that understanding
I'll just immediately try to give it
away okay I'll just immediately try to
hand it to somebody and give it away
why cuz I like
it okay in Buddhism the more you like
something the more you give it away okay
cuz it more will come okay that's all
then that's inexhaustible that's a
positive
samsara that's a cycle and it never ends
and then it's just unending
okay all right then we have finished the
first
quarter of The Diamond Cutter Sutra uh
congratulations so we have a plan for
next
time it was just invented this
morning well last night i' sent you
but we're thinking maybe more people
want to come maybe in
October we'll do uh the second quarter
of The Diamond Cutter
Sutra
uh
right
okay uh then I'm thinking some people
might want to come who didn't come to
the first part so my idea I I the dates
are roughly correct I'm not sure yet
right Michael we're not sure
completely
but
uh
sorry
will for people who want to come to
Master kamila 2 they have to come to
madis kamila number part one you guys
don't have to come to that first part
you already
came but tell other people if they want
to come to part two they have to come to
part one part one will be taught by
Michael Melissa John and Connie I I
think uh before the long R Retreat okay
in October at diam Mountain okay so tell
people if they want to come to kamila
part two they have to come to part one
okay understand it's
blackmail
okay no I mean imagine people coming to
part two without part one it's very
frustrating for me then I have to go
back back to part one you guys never
progress it's very frustrating okay um
you us over the past few days that we
should be teaching this if we do teach
this before October will the people who
take the from us be
able that's a tough question I'd say
it's probably
okay okay if you teach it
well I just listen to it three times and
then teach it okay on different
days all right